Finding Aid for Museum of Art (University of Michigan) Publications, 1946-ongoing
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Museum of Art (University of Michigan) Publications 1946-[ongoing] 1960-2004
University of Michigan. Museum of Art.
9788, Bimu, C450, 2
Publications and other printed material produced by the University of Michigan Museum of Art and its sub-units including annual reports, newsletters, brochures, press releases, posters, ephemera and, most notably, exhibition catalogs.
12 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The publications are received periodically from the Museum of Art (donor no. 3195 ).
The publications are open without restriction.
The University of Michigan Museum of Art (UMMA) houses the second largest art collection in the state of Michigan, offering a rich permanent collection supplemented by an active special exhibition program. In addition, the many and varying art collections assist in teaching at the university. The collections of Chinese and Japanese paintings and ceramics; Old Master and contemporary prints and drawings; and Whistler prints are particularly strong.
The museum was established in its present form in 1946. The University Regents declared in November 1945 that the Museum of Art and Archaeology be abolished and that two separate units (the Museum of Art and the Museum of Archaeology) take its place. At their January 1946 meeting, the Regents further stipulated that the Museum of Art be maintained as "a separate administrative unit for the purpose of collection, conservation, study and exhibition of works of art and the preparation of publications with respect thereunto." The university's art collections had their origins long before 1946, however. Early systematic collecting began in 1855 when Professor Henry S. Frieze purchased a number of art works, chiefly engravings and plaster casts, to illustrate his courses in classical art and archaeology. In 1862 Frieze was instrumental in acquiring the university's first significant original work of art, Randolph Rogers' Nydia, the Blind Flower Girl of Pompeii.
The collection grew sporadically in the following decades, in large part through gifts from individuals as well as from graduating classes. The Henry C. Lewis bequest came to the university in 1895 and contained more than four hundred paintings and other works of art. With a modest budget for acquisitions, the museum's first director, Jean Paul Slusser, maintained a focus on collecting modern painting, sculpture and graphics and was quite successful due to his aesthetic expertise, knowledge of the New York art market and connections with Ann Arbor art organizations. The collection was further supplemented by gifts, including the Carl F. Clarke bequest of French and American landscape paintings and the Margaret Watson Parker bequest in 1936 (transferred to the museum in 1954 and 1955) of more than 600 Asian and Western works including Japanese prints and paintings by James NcNeill Whistler. Dr. Walter R. Parker (Margaret's husband and professor of ophthalmology at the university) further bequeathed funds to house the collection and to support future acquisitions.
During the very early years, efforts were made to display the collections. In 1857-1858 they were housed in the North and South Colleges. Space was allocated in the no longer extant library (newly erected in 1883), but even with the additional space gained when the library was enlarged in 1898 the facility could not adequately accommodate the growing collections. In 1910 the collections were moved to Alumni Memorial Hall, sharing the building with the Fine Arts Department and the Alumni Association. The hall has undergone renovations on several occasions. In 1957-1958, a Unistrut system of internal scaffolding was designed by professor of architecture William Muschenheim and installed in the museum apse. This installation increased gallery space. The Unistrut installation was subsequently removed in the early 1970s. Remodeling in 1966-1967 created additional gallery space; modernized the museum's heating, cooling and lighting systems; and provided areas for storage and behind-the-scenes work. The Museum of Art became Alumni Memorial Hall's sole occupant at this time. In 2003, planning was begun for a major expansion designed to increase the building's capacity by 55,000 square feet, to be used for additional gallery space, an auditorium and classrooms, and for a complete renovation of the existing facility.
Important components of the UMMA's program were added as it continued to expand its exhibitions program. In the late 1950s director Charles Sawyer began presenting museum seminars which, by 1963, had developed into the Museum Practice Program. The program, continued through 1995, provided training for many budding professionals in the museum field and organized numerous successful exhibitions for the UMMA over the years. The Friends of the Museum of Art was founded in 1968. This group supports the UMMA's acquisitions and other programming. Under director Bret Waller, the Docent Program was established in 1975 to provide tours for school classes and other visitors.
The University of Michigan Museum of Art Publications (12 linear feet) include annual reports, brochures, bulletins, calendars, catalogs of museum holdings, directories, exhibition catalogs, newsletters, and press releases. These publications are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Exhibition Publications, and Sub-Unit Publications. The bulk of the publications document the exhibits mounted by the Museum of Art and those developed by other museums that were exhibited at the museum. The Docent Program, Friends of the University of Michigan Museum of Art, and the Museum Practice Program are also documented in the Museum of Art Publications.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Museum of Art. Friends.; University of Michigan. Museum Practice Program.; University of Michigan. Graduate Seminar in Museum Practice.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Museum of Art. Friends.; University of Michigan. Museum Practice Program.; University of Michigan. Graduate Seminar in Museum Practice.
Genre Terms:
Bibliographies.; Pamphlets.; Bulletins.; Calendars.; Exhibition catalogs.; Histories.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Posters.; Press releases.; Programs.
- Unit Publications
  The Unit Publications series contains printed material published specifically by the Museum of Art (UMMA). These publications are defined as being widely distributed and may be published at regular intervals. They are arranged by genre of the publication.
  The Unit Publications series (4 linear feet) includes annual reports documenting the period from 1946 to 1985 and 1992 through 2002. Reports from 1946 to 1985 were submitted for inclusion in the President's Report (call no. Fimu, B3). The Bulletin is a scholarly publications first published by the by the museum in 1950. The Bentley Library holds an incomplete run of this publication (1950-1956, vol. 1, no. 1-7) and its successors the Bulletin, New Series (1965-1977, vol. 1-8), and Bulletin: Museums of Art and Archaeology (1978-1992, vol. 1-10 and 2000-2003, vol. 13-14). The museum also published several calendars announcing the exhibits to be shown in the various galleries of the museum. These include Insight (1999-present), a small magazine format publication with color photographs of artwork displayed in the various highlighted exhibitions. This bi-monthly publication also describes lectures and colloquiums sponsored by the museum, new acquisitions, major gifts or grants, spotlights staff members and docents, and announces new exhibitions. The catalogs feature the prominent works of art at the museum including The Mr. and Mrs. Henry Jewett Greene Memorial Collection of Far Eastern Ceramics which was published in 1971. A second catalog, also in black and white, is entitled Eighty Works in the University of Michigan Museum of Art: A Handbook published in 1974. This catalogue describes, in short essays, notable works of art in the museum. These catalogues describe how the various works came to the university, their provenance, and their significance to the collection. Found under the heading "Manuals" is a series of children's guides to the University of Michigan Museum of Art collections entitled A Child's Walk Through Many Lands at the UMMA. There are separate manuals for Asian art, twentieth century American painting and sculpture, and African art. These guides, published from 1984 to 1987, are filled with puzzles, games, and quizzes designed to help children better appreciate art. Researchers will also find three outsize posters advertising both the museum and the museum website. There is also a significant run of press releases, beginning in 1947 to the present, describing new acquisitions, exhibits, staff changes, and other significant events in the life of the Museum of Art.
  - Annual Reports
    - Museum of Art, 1946-1985, 8 folders (Box 1)
    - Annual Report, 1992-1993, 1993-1994, 1996 (Box 1)
    - Application for General Operating Support, 1997 (Box 1)
    - Annual Report 1998-2002, [2003] (Box 1)
  - Articles
    - The University of Michigan Museum of Art, in Research News, 1971 vol. 22, no. 2-3 (Box 1)
  - Bibliographies
    - List of Available Publications, April 1991, 1991 (Box 1)
  - Bookmarks undated (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - Dance 1991 (Box 1)
    - Gallery Information, undated (Box 1)
    - International Travel Program, 1990-1996 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Michigan Art Museums Reciprocal Membership, undated (Box 1)
    - Museum of Art, [1992-1996] and undated (Box 1)
    - Places to Go and People to See, undated (Box 1)
    - Summer Session, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins
    - Bulletin, 1950-1956 vol. 1, no. 1-7, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Bulletin, 1965-1977 New Series, vol. 1-8, 6 folders (Box 1)
    - Bulletin: Museums of Art and Archaeology
      - 1978-1980 vol. 1-3, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - 1981-1992 vol. 4-10, 7 folders (Box 2)
      - 2000-2003 vol. 13-14, 2 folders (Box 2)
      - 2005-2006 vol. 16 (Box 2)
  - Calendars
    - The Nude, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Calendars (Schedules of Events)
    - Art Exhibitions, 1947-1957 (Box 2)
    - Exhibition Schedule, (scattered), 1959-1990 (Box 2)
    - Exhibitions
      - 1971-1973 (Box 2)
      - 1995-2000 (Box 2)
    - Exhibitions and Special Events, 1992-2000 (Box 2)
    - Insight, 1999-ongoing, 6 folders (Box 2)
    - Museum of Art, 1990-1999, 10 folders (Box 2)
    - Museum of Art...Exhibitions, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
    - Special Events, 1990 (Box 2)
  - Catalogs
    - Eighty Works in the Collection of the University of Michigan Museum of Art: A Handbook, 1979 (Box 3)
    - A Handbook of the Collections of the University of Michigan Museum of Art, undated (Box 3)
    - The Mr. and Mrs. Henry Jewett Greene Memorial Collection of Far Eastern Ceramics, [1971] (Box 3)
    - Illustrated Catalogue of European and American Painting and Sculpture, 1988 (Box 3)
    - A Visit to the Gallery, 1997 (Box 3)
    - Works of Art in the University of Michigan, 1937 (Box 3)
  - Ephemera (includes flyers, greeting cards, invitations, and postcards)
    - 1958-1999 undated, 5 folders (Box 3)
  - Gallery Guides
    - 1996-1997 undated (Box 3)
  - Manuals
    - #2 A Child's Walk Through Many Lands at the UMMA
      - A Child's Walk Through Asia, 1984 (Box 3)
    - #3, A Child's Walk Through Twentieth-Century American Painting and Sculpture, 1985 (Box 3)
    - #4, A Child's Walk Through Africa, 1987 (Box 3)
  - Mission Statements
    - Fulfilling Our Mission, undated (Box 3)
  - Newsletters
    - Newsletter, 1989-1992, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Posters undated (Folder C4520)
    (Outsize Posters, 9788 Bimu, C450, 2)
  - Press Releases
    - 1947-1953 (Box 4)
    - 1956-1960, 5 folders (Box 4)
    - 1963-1965, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - 1967-1974, 8 folders (Box 4)
    - 1986, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - 1991-ongoing, 14 folders (Box 4)
  - Programs
    - A Commemorative Ceremony in Honor of Jean Paul Slusser, 1886-1981, 1981 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1994, 1997-1998 (Box 4)
- Exhibition Publications
  Exhibition Publications (7 linear feet) make up the majority of the University of Michigan Museum of Art Publications. Exhibits are sometimes made up solely of UMMA holdings and are shown only at the museum, but frequently the University of Michigan Museum of Art curators work with other museums to develop major exhibitions which are displayed at the Museum of Art during their travels throughout the country. The publications in this series describe in detail the works of art selected for each exhibit. These catalogs include essays describing the focus of the exhibition as well as a detailed physical description and provenance of each piece. There are often color photographs of the most notable works. In many cases there is a catalog for each exhibit, but for some, particularly the earlier (1946-1960) exhibits there are only ephemeral publications. When extant, flyers, invitations, posters and other publications produced to announce and celebrate each exhibit have been included in the exhibit folder. In this series the exhibition publications are arranged chronologically by the opening date of the exhibit. Though these files are extensive, the Bentley Library does not hold a complete run of these publications. The researcher should consult the manuscript record group for a more complete and comprehensive study of the exhibitions presented at the University of Michigan Museum of Art.
  - Undated
    - California Painting: 40 Painters Selected by Samuel Heavenrich and Grace L. McCann Morley with Statements by the Artists (Box 5)
    - Drawings by Seattle Artists, an Exhibition Prepared by the Seattle Art Museum (Box 5)
    - Eskimo Art of the Canadian Eastern Arctic (Box 5)
    - La More, undated (Box 5)
    - Twentieth Century Art at the University of Michigan, undated (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous undated (Box 5)
  - 1946-1947
    - Pioneers of Modern Art in America, (Rackham Gallery) July 1-21, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Water Colors by Dong Kingman and DeHirsh Margules, October 4-26, 1946 (Box 5)
    - Four Centuries of Tapestry Weaving, November 5-December 1, 1946 (Box 5)
    - African Negro Sculpture, December 4-20, 1946 (Box 5)
    - The Brooklyn Museum First National Print Annual Exhibition, March 19-May 4, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Pedro Figari, 1861-1938, May 1-25, 1947 (Box 5)
  - 1947-1948
    - Paintings Looted from Holland, November 3-28, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Fifty Latin-American Prints, February 1-12, 1948 (Box 5)
  - 1948-1949
    - Drawings and Watercolors from the Collection of John S. Newberry, Jr., September 28-October 24, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Michigan on Canvas, October 28-November 11, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Contemporary Paintings from the Albright Art Gallery, November 4-24, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Privately Owned Art in Ann Arbor, January 6-26, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Accessions to the Collections, July 1947 to December 1948, February 13-March 6, 1949 (Box 5)
    - The Brooklyn Museum Third National Print Annual Exhibition, March 23-May 22, 1949 (Box 5)
    - 18th Century England, May 1-28, 1949 (Box 5)
    - American Printmaking, 1913-1947, May 7-28, 1949 (Box 5)
  - 1949-1950
    - 1848 Year of Revolutions, October 10-November 7, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Accessions to the Collections, 1949, January 7-February 1, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Chinese Buddhist Bronzes, April 13-May 7, 1950 (Box 5)
  - 1950-1951
    - A New Direction in Intaglio, October 15-November 5, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Sport and Circus, November 9-29, 1950 (Box 5)
    - Advancing French Art, March 4-25, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Modern Furniture, March 4-April 4, 1951 (Box 5)
  - 1951-1952
    - Italian, Spanish & French Paintings of the 17th & 18th Centuries, November 1-28, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Sixth Annual Michigan Water Color Society, June 1-29, 1952 (Box 5)
  - 1952-1953
    - Japanese Festival, October 12-November 2, 1952 (Box 5)
    - Watercolors and Drawings by Gavarni, January 2, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Contemporary Italian Prints, January 6-27, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Early Chinese Jades, March 22-April 22, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Annual Exhibition of Student Work, College of Architecture and Design, May 3-31, 1953 (Box 5)
  - 1953-1954
    - Popular Art in America, June 30-August 7, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Purcell and Elmslie: Architects, October 18-November 3, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Framing: Right and Wrong, October 30-November 20, 1953 (Box 5)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Lawrence A. Fleischman Collection of American Paintings, November 15-December 6, 1953 (Box 5)
    - 8th Annual Michigan Water Color Society Exhibition, June 1-12, 1954 (Box 5)
  - 1954-1955
    - Woman in the World of Man: Three Women Painters, Irene Rice Pereira, Kay Sage, Dorothea Tanning, June 20-July 25, 1954 (Box 5)
    - Plastic and Graphic Expressions by Modern Sculptors, November 7-30, 1954 (Box 5)
  - 1955-1956
    - Michigan Art Through Fifty Years, June 26-July 31, 1955 (Box 5)
    - 20th Century Painting and Sculpture, October 30-November 27, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Contemporary Finnish Architecture, February 19-March 11, 1956 (Box 5)
  - 1956-1957
    - Eight New York Painters, July 1-31, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Zen '49 Group, August 22-September 26, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Semi-Centennial Celebration, October 24-November 4, 1956 (Box 5)
    - Calvin Albert: Sculpture and Drawings, March 3-24, 1957 (Box 5)
  - 1957-1958
    - Fourth International Biennial of Contemporary Color Lithography, November 5-20, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Craftsmanship in a Changing World, November 8-23, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Good Design in Switzerland, March 9-30, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Mexican Art: Pre-Columbian to Modern Times, April 17-June 15, 1958 (Box 5)
  - 1958-1959
    - Sculpture Midwest 1957, June 15-September 2, 1958 (Box 5)
    - The New Landscape in Art and Science, October 1-26, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Art Department Faculty, October 16-November 23, 1958 (Box 5)
    - The Brooklyn Museum Eleventh National Print Exhibition, November 1-30, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Rackham Grant Exhibitions (Richard Wilt, Richard Sears, Albert P. Mullen, January 7-March 31, 1959 (Box 5)
    - The American Line Drawings: 100 Years of Drawing, March 1-21, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Persian Art Before and After the Mongol Conquest, April 8-May 17, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Selections from The Edward Root Collection, April 22-June 14, 1959 (Box 5)
  - 1959-1960
    - Fulbright Painters, October 21-November 15, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Mount Sinai and the Monastery of St. Catherine, November 14-December 22, 1959 (Box 5)
    - An Exhibition of Painting in Post-War Italy: 1945-1957, December 5-27, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Rackham Grant Exhibitions (Louis Tavelli, Frank Cassara, Fred Vida r), January 6-April 6, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Architecture in Venezuela, January 12-30, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Contemporary Prints from Italy, February 12-March 9, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Gandhara Sculpture from Pakistan Museums, February 21-March 13, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Images at Mid-Century, April 13-June 12, 1960 (Box 5)
    - The Private World of Pablo Picasso, May 1, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Five Centuries of Drawing, May 15-June 5, 1960 (Box 5)
  - 1960-1961
    - German Artists of Today, June 27, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Contemporary Prints from France, II, September 12-October 16, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Rembrandt Prints, October 23-November 20, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Prints for Christmas, November 16-December 7, 1960 (Box 5)
    - Rackham Grant Exhibitions (Milton Cohen, Albert Weber), January 11-February 12, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Painting on the Surfaces of Domes and Spacegrids (Rackham Grant Exhibition of Gerome Kamrowski and Leonard Zamiska), February 15-March 19, 1961 (Box 5)
    - The Photograph as Poetry, April 8-May 7, 1961 (Box 5)
  - 1961-1962
    - Michigan and the Civil War, June 28-August 13, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Latin America: New Departures, October 15-November 12, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Bay Printmakers' Society Sixth National Exhibition, October 15-November 14, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Rackham Grant Exhibitions I (Thomas F. McClure, Richard Wilt, Chet H. LaMore), November 15-December 10, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Great Book Illustrations of the 15th and 16th Centuries, February 1962 (Box 5)
    - Sculpture and Sculptors' Drawings and Prints, March 4-25, 1962 (Box 5)
    - The Art of Jens Jensen: Landscape Architect, April 18-May 14, 1962 (Box 5)
    - A Generation of Draughtsmen, April 25-May 29, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Contemporary Prints from Japan, June 23-August 25, 1962 (Box 5)
  - 1962-1963
    - Contemporary American Painting: Selections from the Neuberger Collection, October 21-November 18, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Chi-Kwan Chen: A Decade in Retrospect, November 28-December 16, 1962 (Box 5)
    - Art Nouveau Sampler, December 15, 1962-January 20, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Contemporary Watercolors and Drawings for Purchase Consideration, January 13-February 10, 1963 (Box 5)
    - The Ideal Theater: Eight Concepts, February 21-April 2, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Marcel Breuer: Architect, March 1-17, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Contemporary European Painting for Purchase Consideration, April 17-May 19, 1963 (Box 5)
  - 1963-1964
    - Six Painters and the Object, October 9-November 3, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Leon Dabo (1868-1960): A Retrospective Exhibition, November 13-December 8, 1963 (Box 5)
    - The New Formalists: Paintings for Purchase Consideration, January 15-February 9, 1964 (Box 5)
    - European Posters, January 18-February 9, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Indian Miniatures (Archer Collection), February 12-April 6, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Ideas in Images: An Exhibition of 100 Photographs, February 21-March 13, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Lithographs from the Tamarind Workshop, March 4-April 12, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Italy Through Dutch Eyes: Dutch Seventeenth Century Landscape Artists in Italy, April 22-May 24, 1964 (Box 5)
  - 1964-1965
    - Modern Japanese Calligraphy, June 21-September 27, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Paintings and Drawings by Hale Woodruff, June 24-July 19, 1964 (Box 5)
    - Designed for Production: The Craftsman's Approach, October 7-31, 1964 (Box 5)
    - American Drawings, November 11-December 13, 1964 (Box 5)
    - William Blake: Poet, Printer, Prophet, January 16-February 14, 1965 (Box 5)
    - One Hundred Contemporary American Drawings, February 24-March 28, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Architectural and Ornament Drawings of the 16th to the early 19th Centuries in the Collection of the University of Michigan Museum of Art, May 26-June 27, 1965 (Box 5)
  - 1965-1966
    - Contemporary Prints from Germany II, June 29-August 15, 1965 (Box 6)
    - 23rd National Ceramics Exhibition, July 5-August 14, 1965 (Box 6)
    - French Watercolors (1750-1850), September 29-October 24, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Paintings & Drawings & Sculptures from the Collection of Caroline and Erwin Swann, November 3-December 5, 1965 (Box 6)
    - Reflections: the Image of Man, December 5, 1965-January 16, 1966 (Box 6)
    - [Contemporary] Japanese Abstract Art, January 19-February 27, 1966 (Box 6)
    - The Architecture of Jacques Brownson, April 6-May 8, 1966 (Box 6)
  - 1966-1967
    - Alessandro Magnasco (1667-1749), April 23-May 14, 1967 (Box 6)
  - 1967-1968
    - The Painting of Tao-Chi August 13-September 17, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Sasanian Silver: Late Antique and Early Medieval Arts of Luxury from Iran, August 13-September 17, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Michigan Alumni Art Collections: Works of Art Selected from the Collections of Alumni of the University of Michigan, October 1-29, 1967 (Box 6)
    - Alcoa Collection of Contemporary Art, March 17-April 7, 1968 (Box 6)
    - 15th and 16th Century European Drawings, May 5-26, 1968 (Box 6)
  - 1968-1969
    - A Collection in Progress, October 5-November 3, 1968 (Box 6)
    - English Revivalism 1750-1870 The Aesthetic of Nostalgia, December 8, 1968-January 19, 1969 (Box 6)
    - Manet and Spain, January 19-March 2, 1969 (Box 6)